Preliminary Guide to the A. Hollis Edens Records,1949 - 1960
Duke University. University Archives
- Subject Files
  - Hobbs, Marcus Edwin (Box 46)
  - Hope Valley Country Club (Box 46)
  - Hopkins, Everett H. (Box 46)
  - Hospital Care Association (Box 46)
  - Hungary -- Refugees (Box 46)
  - I Correspondence (Box 46)
  - Institute for Defense Analyses (Box 46)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (Box 46)
  - Institute of International Education (Box 46)
  - Institute of World Affairs, Inc. (Box 46)
  - Intercollegiate Music Council (Box 46)
  - International Academy of the Arts (Box 46)
  - International Association of Universities, [2 folders] (Box 46)
  - International Greek New Testament Project (Box 46)
  - International New Testament Manuscripts Project (Box 46)
  - International Universities Bureau (Box 46)
  - Correspondence (Box 46)
    - Ja-Johnson, L. (Box 46)
    - Johnson, M.-Jz (Box 47)
  - Jackson College, Honolulu, Hawaii (Box 47)
  - Jones, Edwin L. (Box 47)
  - Jordan, Charles Edward (Box 47)
  - Junior Science Symposium (Box 47)
  - Correspondence (Box 47)
    - Ka-Kep (Box 47)
    - Ker-Kz (Box 47)
  - Kearns, Gurney Harris, Foundation (Box 47)
  - Kempner Foundation (Box 47)
  - Kimball, Christine A. (Box 48)
  - Kresge Foundation (Box 48)
  - Correspondence (Box 48)
    - La-Lee (Box 48)
    - Lef-Lon (Box 48)
    - Loo-Lz (Box 48)
  - Lambeth, J. Walter (Box 48)
  - Lincoln Hospital -- Durham, NC (Box 48)
  - Correspondence (Box 48)
    - Maa-Mack (Box 48)
    - Macl-Mars (Box 48)
    - Mart-Mei (Box 49)
    - Mej-Mil (Box 49)
    - Mim-Mz (Box 49)
  - McConnell, Robert Earl, Foundation (Box 49)
  - Manchester, Alan Krebs, [2 folders] (Box 49)
  - Marburg Affiliation (Box 49)
  - Markle Foundation, [2 folders] (Box 50)
  - Marshall Scholarships (Box 50)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology -- Cambridge, MA (Box 50)
  - Medical Education (Box 50)
  - Memorial Church Fund (Box 50)
  - Methodist Church, [2 folders] (Box 50)
  - Methodist Church, [1 folders] (Box 51)
  - Methodist Church (Box 51)
    - Board of Education (Box 51)
    - Division of Educational Institutions (Box 51)
    - Ecumenical Consultation Commission (Box 51)
    - General Conference (Box 51)
      - 1952 (Box 51)
      - 1956 (Box 51)
    - General Conference Commission on Christian Higher Education, [3 folders] (Box 51)
    - General Conference Commission on Christian Higher Education - Committee on Negro Education (Box 52)
    - Institute of Higher Education (Box 52)
    - Joint Committee on Public Relations for Education Institutions (Box 52)
    - Methodist-Related University Presidents' Meetings (Box 52)
    - North Carolina Conference, [2 folders] (Box 52)
    - Southeastern Jurisdiction Layman's Conference (Box 52)
    - Southeastern Jurisdictional Conference (Box 52)
      - 1952 (Box 52)
      - 1956 (Box 52)
    - University Senate, [1 folder] (Box 52)
    - University Senate, [4 folders] (Box 53)
    - Western North Carolina Conference, [2 folders] (Box 53)
  - Methodist College -- Fayetteville, NC (Box 53)
  - Methodist College Foundation of North Caroliina (Box 54)
  - Methodist Youth Fellowship (Box 54)
  - Mullen, Thomas R. (Box 54)
  - Murray, William D. (Box 54)
  - N Correspondence (Box 54)
  - National Academy of Sciences -- National Research Council (Box 54)
  - National Association of Manufacturers (Box 54)
  - National Association of Schools and Colleges of the Methodist Church (Box 54)
  - National Collegiate Athletic Association (Box 54)
  - National Commission on Accrediting, [3 folders] (Box 54)
  - National Commission on Accrediting, [4 folders] (Box 55)
  - National Commission on Accrediting (Box 55)
    - Minutes and Correspondence [see also boxes 80 and 81] (Box 55)
  - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (Box 55)
  - National Education Association (Box 55)
  - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, Inc. (Box 55)
  - National Fund for Medical Education (Box 55)
  - National Heart Committee (Box 55)
  - National Industrial Conference Board (Box 55)
  - National Institutes of Health (Box 55)
  - National Institutes of Health (Box 55)
  - National Merit Scholarship Corporation (Box 56)
  - National Planning Association, [2 folders] (Box 56)
  - National Planning Association (Box 56)
    - Canadian-American Committee, [4 folders] (Box 56)
    - Canadian-American Committee, [6 folders] (Box 57)
  - National Resources Conference (Box 57)
  - National Science Foundation (Box 58)
  - National Youth Scholarship Contest (Box 58)
  - Naval ROTC -- North Carolina State Selection Committee (Box 58)
  - Newcomen Society (Box 58)
  - Nixon, Richard Milhouse (Box 58)
  - Noble, Edward John, Foundation (Box 58)
  - North Carolina (Box 58)
    - Advisory Committee on Scientific, Engineering, and Specialized Personnel (Box 58)
    - Board of Higher Education (Box 58)
    - Resource-Use Education Commission (Box 58)
    - University (Box 58)
    - University [Chapel Hill] (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Academy of Science (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Association of Certified Public Accountants (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Citizens Association, Inc. (Box 58)
  - North Carolina College Conference (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Education Association (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Methodist Student Movement (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Press Association (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Principals' Association (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Student Legislature (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Wesleyan College -- Rocky Mount, NC (Box 58)
  - North Carolina Wildlife Federation (Box 58)
  - O Correspondence (Box 59)
  - Oak Ridge Institute of Nuclear Studies (Box 59)
  - Ogburn, Charlton (Box 59)
  - Orange Bowl (Box 59)
  - Ozanne, Charles E. (Box 59)
  - Correspondence (Box 59)
    - Pa-Pd (Box 59)
    - Pe-Ph (Box 59)
    - Pi-Pz (Box 59)
  - Paty, Raymond R. (Box 59)
  - Phelps-Stokes Fund (Box 59)
  - Phi Beta Kappa (Box 60)
  - Phi Kappa Sigma (Box 60)
  - Phillips, Duncan (Box 60)
  - Phillips Brooks Club -- Durham, NC (Box 60)
  - Polycultural Institute of America (Box 60)
  - Porter, Earl W. (Box 60)
  - President's Committee on Education Beyond the High School, [6 folders] (Box 60)
  - Purks, Harris (Box 61)
  - Q Correspondence (Box 61)
  - Questionnaires (Box 61)
  - Correspondence (Box 61)
    - Ra-Ree (Box 61)
    - Ref-Ric (Box 61)
    - Rid-Roc (Box 61)
    - Rod-Rz (Box 61)
  - Race Problems (Box 62)
  - Randolph-Macon College -- Ashland, VA (Box 62)
  - Regional University Patent Policy Conference -- Atlanta, GA (Box 62)
  - Research Triangle Park, [5 folders] (Box 62)
  - Research Triangle Park, [1 folder] (Box 63)
  - Rhine, Joseph Banks (Box 63)
  - Richardson Foundation (Box 63)
  - Richey, McMurry S. (Box 63)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 63)
  - Rotary Club (Box 63)
  - Correspondence (Box 63)
    - Sa-Seb (Box 63)
    - Sec-Sh (Box 63)
    - Si-Smith, B. (Box 64)
    - Smith, C.-Smz (Box 64)
    - Sn-Sq (Box 64)
    - Sr-Stf (Box 64)
    - Stq-Sz (Box 64)
  - Sample, Paul L. (Box 64)
  - Sands, Alexander Hamilton, Jr., [2 folders] (Box 65)
  - Scrolls (Box 65)
  - Seeman, Ernest Albright (Box 65)
  - Shell Fellowship Committee (Box 65)
  - Sibley, John A. (Box 65)
  - Sigma Chi (Box 65)
  - Smith, Willis (Box 65)
  - Social Science Research Council, [2 folders] (Box 65)
  - SOUTH ATLANTIC QUARTERLY (Box 65)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, [1 folder] (Box 65)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, [8 folders] (Box 66)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, [4 folders] (Box 67)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools -- Tulane Material, [3 folders] (Box 67)
  - Southern Association of Science and Industry (Box 68)
  - Southern College Personnel Association (Box 68)
  - Southern Conference (Box 68)
  - Southern Conference Educational Fund (Box 68)
  - Southern Education Reporting Service (Box 68)
  - Southern Humanities Conference (Box 68)
  - Southern Political Science Association (Box 68)
  - Southern Regional Education Board, [4 folders] (Box 68)
  - Southern Regional Education Board, [2 folders] (Box 69)
  - Southern University Conference (Box 69)
  - Strauss, Harry H. (Box 69)
  - Subversive Activities (Box 69)
  - Sweet Briar College -- Sweet Briar, VA (Box 69)
  - Correspondence (Box 70)
    - Ta-Th (Box 70)
    - Ti-Tz (Box 70)
  - Taxation (Box 70)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association (Box 70)
  - Teaching, Freedom of (Box 70)
  - TIME Magazine (Box 70)
  - Trumbauer, Horace -- Memorial Fund (Box 70)
  - Tschaikovsky Foundation (Box 70)
  - Tuition Exchange -- Williamstown, MA (Box 70)
  - Tuthill, Richard L. (Box 70)
  - U Correspondence (Box 70)
  - United Fund of Durham and Durham County, [1 folder] (Box 70)
  - United Fund of Durham and Durham County, [3 folders] (Box 71)
  - U. S. (Box 71)
    - Air Force (Box 71)
      - Air Training Command Advisory Board, [2 folders] (Box 71)
      - Research and Development (Box 71)
    - Armed Forces (Box 71)
    - Army - Mathematics Center (Box 71)
    - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 71)
    - Congress - House of Representatives Special Committee to Investigate Tax Exempt Foundations (Box 71)
    - Defense Department Joint Advisory Panel on ROTC Affairs, [4 folders] (Box 72)
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 72)
    - Federal Security Agency Office of Education (Box 72)
    - Health, Education, and Welfare Department Office of Education (Box 72)
    - Navy Training Cruise (Box 72)
    - Post Office Department (Box 72)
    - Selective Service System (Box 72)
    - State Department (Box 72)
    - State Department Foreign Service Advisory Committee (Box 72)
    - State Department International Educational Exchange Service, [3 folders] (Box 72)
    - State Department International Educational Exchange Service [Oversize Material] (Box 72)
    - Veterans Administration (Box 72)
  - University Club -- New York, NY (Box 72)
  - Urey, Harold C. (Box 72)
  - V Correspondence (Box 72)
  - Virginia University -- Mountain Lake Biological Station (Box 72)
  - Correspondence (Box 73)
    - Wa-Wd (Box 73)
    - We-Wg (Box 73)
    - Wh (Box 73)
    - Wi-Wn (Box 73)
    - Wo-Wz (Box 73)
  - Wake Forest University -- Winston-Salem, NC (Box 73)
  - White House Conference on Education (Box 73)
  - Woodberry Forest School -- Woodberry Forest, VA (Box 73)
  - World Council of Churches, [2 folders] (Box 74)
  - World Methodist Council (Box 74)
  - World Student Service Fund (Box 74)
  - XYZ Correspondence (Box 74)
  - Yale University -- New Haven, CN - Human Relations Area Files (Box 74)
  - Young Men's Christian Association -- Durham, NC (Box 74)
  - Bound Report: "Proposed Establishment of a Social Studies Research & Training Center at Duke University" (Box 74)
- U. S. State Department's Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange (Box 74)
  - Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange (Box 75)
  - Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange (Box 76)
  - Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange (Box 77)
  - Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange (Box 78)
  - Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange (Box 79)
- National Commission on Accrediting (Box 79)
  - Minutes and Correspondence [continued from Box 55] (Box 80)
  - Minutes and Correspondence (Box 81)
- Inauguration (Box 81)
  - Inauguration Papers [see also Box 38] (Box 82)
  - Inauguration Papers (Box 83)
  - Inauguration Papers (Box 84)
  - Inauguration Papers (Box 85)
- Annual Reports to the President (Box 85)
  - 1949: Divinity School, Educational Division, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Library, Medical School, Public Relations, Research Council, Student Life, Trinity College, Woman's College, Engineering College (Box 86)
  - 1950: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School (Box 86)
  - 1950: Graduate School, Law School, Library, Medical School, Public Relations, Research Council, Student Life, Summer Session, Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 87)
  - 1951: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Edited Summaries, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Library, Medical School (Box 87)
  - 1951: Public Relations, Research Council, Student Life, Summer Session, Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 88)
  - 1952: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Law School, Medical School, Public Relations (Box 88)
  - 1952: Library, Research Council, Student Life, Summer Session, Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 89)
  - 1953: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Medical School, Public Relations, Research Council, Student Life, Summer Session, Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 89)
  - 1954: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Library, Medical School, Public Relations, Research Council, Student Life, Summer Session, Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 90)
  - 1955: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Library, Medical School, Public Relations, Registrar, Research Council, Student Life, Summer Session (Box 91)
  - 1955: Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 92)
  - 1956: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Library, Medical School, Physical Education, Public Relations, Research Council, Student Life (Box 92)
  - 1956: Summer Session, Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 93)
  - 1957: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Library, Medical School, Public Relations, Research Council, Student Life (Box 93)
  - 1957: Summer Session, Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 94)
  - 1958: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Library, Medical School, Physical Education and Athletics, Public Relations, Research Council (Box 94)
  - 1958: Student Life, Summer Session, Trinity College, Woman's College (Box 95)
  - 1959: Divinity School, Duke University Press, Educational Division, Engineering College, Financial Reports, Forestry School, Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, Law School, Libraries, Long Range Planning (Box 95)
  - 1959: Medical Center, Registrar, Research Council, Public Relations, Secretary, Student Life, Summer Session, Trinity College, Undergraduate Studies, Woman's College (Box 96)
  - 1960: Athletics, Divinity School, Duke University Press (Box 96)
  - 1960: Engineering School, Forestry School, Graduate School, Law School, Librarian, Medical School, Nursing School, Public Relations, Registrar, Secretary, Student Life, Summer Session, Trinity College, Undergraduate Studies, Woman's College (Box 97)
  - Miscellaneous Annual Reports (Box 97)
  - Annual Reports to President Robert Lee Flowers (Box 97)
- Assistant to the President, Earl W. Porter (1956-1960) (Box 97)
  - Miscellaneous folders, including general correspondence,1958-1959 (Box 98)
  - Miscellaneous folders, including visit of the President of Ghana and general statistical reports (Box 99)
  - Memoranda, general correspondence (1957), reports to the Board of Trustees, and miscellaneous folders (Box 100)
  - General reports, speeches, recommendations, miscellany (Box 101)
- Segregation Policy -- Petitions (Box 101)
  - Segregation policy petitions (Box 102)
- U.S. State Department, International Education (Box 102)
  - U.S. State Department, International Education materials (Box 102)
- Gross-Edens Controversy [RESTRICTED] (Box 102)
  - Correspondence, proposals, and reports related to administrative decisions and long-range planning for Duke University [RESTRICTED] (Box 103)
- Oversize Materials (Box 103)
  - Inauguration (Box 103)
    - Presentations, Tape Recordings, Film,1949 (Box 104)
Related Material
[Forms part of:] Duke University President records.
University Archives. Duke University.
Gross-Edens Affair Subject Files.
University Archives. Duke University.
Paul M. Gross Papers.
University Archives. Duke University.